JORDAN CHAMBERLIN

Agricultural Economist International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) CIMMYT–Kenya, ICRAF House, United Nations Avenue, PO Box 1041, Nairobi 00621 Kenya

 Email: j.chamberlin@cgiar.org
 ORCID: 0000-0001-9522-3001

 Skype: luckywinner1
 Scopus Author ID: 7005396229

 Phone: +254 783 289557
 Web of Science: AAI-7139-2020

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I conduct applied research on rural development and economic growth, with an emphasis on smallholder agriculture and rural household welfare in developing countries. I am particularly interested in how rural households participate in the transformational changes currently taking place in the developing world – particularly in sub-Saharan Africa – in terms of who wins and who loses, and how we account for such tradeoffs over different timeframes and scopes of analysis. My work emphasizes microeconomic foundations for conceptualizing such processes and their impacts on decision-making processes of interest. Areas of recent research include: smallholder access to land under evolving land institutions in sub-Saharan Africa; the efficiency of market intermediation services; the provision of infrastructure and other public goods; and small town development. In addition to traditional microeconomic and econometric research methods, my work often incorporates theoretical and empirical approaches which are explicitly spatial in nature, including spatial econometric methods and geographic information science. Much of my work has involved the design and collection of household survey data, although more recently I have also used randomized control trials to measure intervention impacts.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Spatial Economist (Senior Scientist), International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center, Nairobi, Kenya (2015-present)

Assistant Professor, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan (2013-2015)

Scientist, International Food Policy Research Institute, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia (2004-2008)

Research Analyst/GIS Specialist, International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington, DC, USA (2001-2004)

EDUCATION

PhD, Agricultural Economics, 2013: Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, USA. Specialization: Rural Infrastructure Investments and Market Access for Smallholder Farmers. Advisor: T. S. Jayne

MA, Geography, 1999: Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ, USA.

Specialization: Application of Remote Sensing and Geographic Information Systems

Technologies to Environmental Resource Management in Latin America. Advisor: R. Sierra

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS (SINCE 2013)

Abay, K., G. Berhane, B. Koru, and J. **Chamberlin**. 2021. "Does Rainfall Variability Explain Low Uptake of Agricultural Credit? Evidence from Ethiopia." *European Review of Agricultural Economics*. *Accepted*

Abay, K., J. **Chamberlin**, G. Berhane. 2021. "Are Land Rental Markets Responding to Rising Population Pressures and Land Scarcity in sub-Saharan Africa?" *Land Use Policy* 101(February 2021): 105139. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landusepol.2020.105139

Bonilla Cedrez, C., J. **Chamberlin**, and R.J. Hijmans. 2020. "Seasonal, Annual and Spatial Variation in Cereal Prices in Sub-Saharan Africa." *Global Food Security* 26(September 2020): 100438. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2020.100438

Palmas, S., and J. **Chamberlin**. 2020. "A Spatial Ex Ante Analysis of Fertilizer Profitability in Tanzania." *PLoS ONE* 15(9): e0239149. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0239149

Abay, K., H. Ayalew, W. Asnake, J. **Chamberlin** and J. Sumberg. 2020. "Landscapes of opportunity: Patterns of young people's engagement with the rural economy in sub-Saharan Africa" *The Journal of Development Studies* https://doi.org/10.1080/00220388.2020.1808195

Chamberlin, J., T. S. Jayne, and N. J. Sitko. 2020. "Rural In-Migration and Agricultural Development: Evidence from Zambia." *Agricultural Economics* 51(4):491-504 https://doi.org/10.1111/agec.12567

Chamberlin, J. and T.S. Jayne. 2020. "Does farm structure affect rural household incomes? Evidence from Tanzania." *Food Policy* 90(2020):101805. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodpol.2019.101805

Bonilla Cedrez, C., J. **Chamberlin**, Z. Guo. and R. J. Hijmans. 2020. "Spatial variation in fertilizer prices in Sub-Saharan Africa." PLoS ONE 15(1): e0227764. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0227764

Assefa, B.T., J. **Chamberlin**, P. Reidsma, J. Vasco Silva, and M.K. van Ittersum. 2019. "Unravelling the variability and causes of smallholder maize yield gaps in Ethiopia." *Food Security* 12(1):83-103. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12571-019-00981-4.

Ricker-Gilbert, J., J. **Chamberlin**, J. Kanyamuka, C.B.L. Jumbe, R. Lunduka, and S. Kaiyatsa. 2019. "How do Informal Farmland Rental Markets Affect Smallholders' Well-being? Evidence from a Matched Tenant-Landlord Survey in Malawi." *Agricultural Economics* (2019) DOI: https://doi.org/10.1111/agec.12512

Oyinbo, O., **Chamberlin**, J., Vanlauwe, B., Vranken, L., Kamara, A., Craufurd, P. & M. Maertens. 2019. "Farmers' preferences for high-input agriculture supported by site-specific extension services: evidence from a choice experiment in Nigeria." *Agricultural Systems*, 173, 12-26. DOI: https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2019.02.003

Jayne, T. S., J. **Chamberlin** and R. Benfica. 2018. "Africa's Unfolding Economic Transformation: Introduction to the Special Issue on Economic Transformation in Sub-Saharan Africa." *Journal of Development Studies* 54(5). https://doi.org/10.1080/00220388.2018.1430774

Ricker-Gilbert, J., and J. **Chamberlin**. 2018. "Transaction Costs, Land Rental Markets and Their Impact on Youth Access to Agriculture in Tanzania." *Land Economics* 94:4 (November 2018). http://doi.org/10.3368/le.94.4.541

Alwang, J., E. Gotor, G. Thiele, G. Hareau, M. Jaleta, and J. **Chamberlin**. 2019. "Pathways from research on improved staple crop germplasm to poverty reduction for smallholder farmers." *Agricultural Systems* 172:16-27 (June 2019). http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2017.10.005

Ripoll, Santiago, Jens Andersson, Lone Badstue, Marion Büttner, Jordan **Chamberlin**, Olaf Erenstein and James Sumberg. 2017. "Rural transformation, cereals and youth in Africa: What role for international agricultural research?" *Outlook on Agronomy* 46(3): 2017. https://doi.org/10.1177/0030727017724669

Sitko, Nicholas, Jordan **Chamberlin**, Benedito Cunguara, Milu Muyanga and Julius Mangisoni. 2017. "A comparative political economic analysis of maize sector policies in eastern and southern Africa." *Food Policy* 69:243–255. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodpol.2017.04.010

Chamberlin, Jordan and Jacob Ricker-Gilbert. 2016. "What are the Drivers of Rural Land Rental Markets in sub-Saharan Africa, and how do they Impact Household Welfare? Evidence from Malawi and Zambia." *American Journal of Agricultural Economics* 98(5): 1507-1528. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajae/aaw021

Jayne, T.S., Jordan **Chamberlin**, Lulama Traub, Nicholas Sitko, Milu Muyanga, Felix K. Yeboah, Ward Anseeuw, Antony Chapoto, Ayala Wineman, Chewe Nkonde and Richard Kachule. 2016. "Africa's Changing Farm Size Distribution Patterns: The Rise of Medium-Scale Farms." *Agricultural Economics* 47s:197-214. https://doi.org/10.1111/agec.12308

Sitko, Nicholas, and Jordan **Chamberlin**. 2016. "The geography of Zambia's customary land: Assessing the prospects for smallholder development." *Land Use Policy* 55:49–60.

Hichaambwa, Munguzwe, Jordan **Chamberlin**, and Nicholas Sitko. 2015. "Determinants and welfare effects of smallholder participation in horticultural markets in Zambia." *African Journal of Agricultural and Resource Economics* 10(4):279-296.

Sitko, Nicholas, and Jordan **Chamberlin**. 2015. "The Anatomy of Medium-Scale Farm Growth in Zambia: What Are the Implications for the Future of Smallholder Agriculture?" *Land* 2015(4):869-887.

Sitko, Nicholas, Jordan **Chamberlin** and Munguzwe Hichaambwa. 2014. "Does Smallholder Land Titling Facilitate Agricultural Growth? An Analysis of the Determinants and Effects of Smallholder Land Titling in Zambia." *World Development* 64:791–802.

Chamberlin, Jordan, T. S. Jayne, and Derek Headey. 2014. "Scarcity Amidst Abundance? Reassessing the Potential for Cropland Expansion in Africa." *Food Policy* 48:51-65.

Jayne, T.S., Jordan **Chamberlin** and Derek Headey. 2014. "Land Pressures, the Evolution of Farming Systems, and Development Strategies in Africa: A Synthesis." *Food Policy* 48:1-17.

Ricker-Gilbert, Jacob, Charles Jumbe, and Jordan **Chamberlin**. 2014. "The Impact of Increasing Population Density on African Agriculture and Livelihoods: The Case of Malawi." *Food Policy* 48:114-128.

Jayne, T.S., Antony Chapoto, Nicholas Sitko, Chewe Nkonde, Milu Muyanga, and Jordan **Chamberlin**. 2014. "Is the Scramble for Land in Africa Foreclosing a Smallholder Agricultural Expansion Strategy?" *Journal of International Affairs* Spring 2014.

Chamberlin, Jordan and T.S. Jayne. 2013. "Unpacking the Meaning of "Market Access"." *World Development* 41:245–264.

JOURNAL SPECIAL ISSUES

Jayne, T.S., Jordan **Chamberlin** and Rui Benfica (Editors of special issue). 2018. "The Role of Agricultural Transformation within Africa's Economic Development Process." *Journal of Development Studies*: 5/4 (2018).

Jayne, T.S., Derek Headey and Jordan **Chamberlin** (Editors of special issue). 2014. "Boserup and Beyond: Mounting Land Pressures and Development Strategies in Africa". *Food Policy*, Volume 48, Pages 1-202 (October 2014).

Books

Jayne, T. S., Jordan **Chamberlin**, and Rui Benfica (editors). 2019. *The Transformation of Rural Africa*. Routledge: New York. ISBN13: 978-1-138-32549-4

BOOK CHAPTERS

Oosterom, M., J. **Chamberlin** and J. Sumberg. 2021 (forthcoming). "Empirical windows on African rural youth." Chapter 2 in Sumberg, J. (editor), *Youth and the Rural Economy in Africa: Hard Work and Hazard*, CABI Publishing, pp. 23-42.

Chamberlin, J., F. K. Yeboah and J. Sumberg. 2021 (forthcoming). "Young people and land." Chapter 4 in Sumberg, J. (editor), *Youth and the Rural Economy in Africa: Hard Work and Hazard*, CABI Publishing, pp 58-77.

Chamberlin, J. and J. Sumberg. 2021 (forthcoming). "Are young people transforming the rural economy?" Chapter 6 in Sumberg, J. (editor), *Youth and the Rural Economy in Africa: Hard Work and Hazard*, CABI Publishing, pp. 92-124.

Sumberg, J., C. Szyp, T. Yeboah, M. Oosterom, B. Crossouard and J. **Chamberlin**. 2021 (forthcoming). "Young people and the rural economy: synthesis and implications." Chapter 10 in Sumberg, J. (editor), *Youth and the Rural Economy in Africa: Hard Work and Hazard*, CABI Publishing, pp. 173-180.

Chamberlin, J. and E. Schmidt. 2013. "Ethiopian Agriculture: A Dynamic Geographic Perspective." Chapter 2 in Dorosh, P. and Rashid, S. (editors), *Food and Agriculture in Ethiopia: Progress and Policy Challenges*. International Food Policy Research Institute and University of Pennsylvania press.

RECENT UNIVERSITY SERVICE AND TEACHING

External PhD advisor/committee member: KU Leuven (Bioeconomics), Wageningen University (Plant Production Systems), Purdue University (Agricultural Economics), University of Minnesota (Applied Economics).

RECENT GRANTS

International Food Policy Research Institute (2018-2020). Policies, Institutions and Markets CRP Flagship 2 project "Ongoing transformations in Africa's rural factor markets: Implications for growth, productivity and welfare." (PI: Chamberlin) 240,000 USD.

Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation (2019-20). "Taking Maize Agronomy to Scale in Africa" (PI: Chamberlin) 1,300,000 USD.

USAID (2019-20). Innovation Lab for Sustainable Intensification: Geospatial and Farming Systems Consortium. "Spatial profitability of alternative production strategies in maize-based smallholder farming systems in sub-Saharan Africa." (PI: Chamberlin) 200,000 USD.

CGIAR Gender Platform (2019). "Rural Out-Migration and the Feminization of Agriculture in sub-Saharan Africa: A Multi-Country, Mixed-Methods Study" (PI: Chamberlin) 50,000 USD.

WORKING LANGUAGES

English (native), Spanish (fluent), Portuguese (operational), Amharic (basic)